Guide to the Picturing Activism student projects, 2017 RL.11659
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Picturing Activism student projects
2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
RL.11659
1.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes; 2 optical disks 31 items
Collection consists of seven creative projects produced by students in the class "Picturing Activism," taught by Lisa McCarty in Fall 2017 at Duke University. The projects utilize archival and contemporary photographs, narrative, poetry, illustrations, digital documents, posters, and oral history interviews in digital audio format to explore themes related to activism, cultural experiences, and visual culture. Subjects include murals in Durham, N.C.; activism in Alamance County, N.C.; African American women, racism, and political activism; environmental crises and activism through photography; pit bull rescues and animal rights; and Chinese cooking as cultural expression. Some of the archival photographs are from the Rubenstein Library's collections. Aquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
7 small volumes; 12 posters; 1 CD-R; 1 DVD
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by student last name.
HIstorical Note
Affiliated with the Duke University Liberal Studies Program, the course, Picturing Activism, was taught by Lisa McCarty in Fall 2017. The students explored how images have been intentionally composed, collected, and deployed to serve as catalysts for social and political change.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Electronic formats are open for research. Original media such as optical discs are closed to use; digital files are available.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Picturing Activism student projects were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The project publications have a variety of gatherings and bindings, including paperback, looseleaf album, and spiral-bound. Most are inkjet printed.
Content Description
Collection consists of seven creative projects produced by students in the class "Picturing Activism," taught by Lisa McCarty in Fall 2017 at Duke University. The projects utilize archival and contemporary photographs, narrative, poetry, illustrations, digital documents, posters, and oral history interviews in digital audio format to explore themes related to activism, cultural experiences, and visual culture. Subjects include murals in Durham, N.C.; activism in Alamance County, N.C.; African American women, racism, and political activism; environmental crises and activism through photography; pit bull rescues and animal rights; and Chinese cooking as cultural expression. Some of the archival photographs are from the Rubenstein Library's collections. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Activists; College students -- North Carolina -- Durham; Documentary Photography -- United States; Photography -- Study and teaching; Visual literacy -- Study and teaching; Visual perception -- Social aspects; Young photographers -- North Carolina -- Durham; Durham (N.C.) -- Photographs; CD-Rs; Color photographs; Digital audio formats; DVDs; Electronic documents; Oral histories (document genre); Photobooks; Posters; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Duke University. Liberal Studies Program; Duke University. Liberal Studies Program
- Fall semester, 2017
  - Cao, Yuqiao. Ephe[mural], 2017; 1 items 1 photobook
    - Ephe[mural], photobook (Box 1)
  - Fladger, Latoya D. Black girl tired, spoken word poetry collection, 2017; 1 items 1 spiral-bound book
    - Black girl tired, spiral-bound book (Box 1)
  - Riley, Sharon. Earth on the line, 2017 November; 3 items 1 folder; 1 CD-R 2 paperback photobooks; 2 Adobe Acrobat .pdf files
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original media closed to use. For access to the digital files, please contact the Rubenstein Library.
    Scope and Contents
    The Adobe Acrobat .pdf documents contain copies of the contents of the photobook; one is the full version; the other is a shorter version for a class presentation.
    - Earth on the line photobook, 2 copies (Box 1)
    - Earth on the line, pdf files (Digital-materials RL11659-SET-0001, E-folder RL11659-CD-0001, Box 1, Data-cd RL11659-CD-0001)
      Original media such as optical discs are closed to use; digital files are available.
  - Hissong, Courtney Davis. #I am Merit, 2017; 13 items 1 accordion photo album; 12 posters
    - #I Am Merit, photograph album (Box 1)
    - #I Am Merit, posters for the Pit Bull Foundation, 12 Sheets 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Shannahan, Maryanne. Activism in Alamance County, 2017 November; 3 items 1 folder; 1 DVD 1 photograph album; 8 .wav files on a DVD
    - Activism in Alamance County, photobook (Box 1)
    - Activism in Alamance County, audio oral history interviews, 8 Files 8 interviews, 8 .wav files (Digital-materials RL11659-SET-0001, E-folder RL11659-DVD-0001, Box 1, Audio-cd RL11659-DVD-0001)
      Original media closed to use; digital files are available.
  - Zang, Yamei. Cooking as a way of life: Chinese international students' cooking at Duke, 2017; 1 items 1 illustrated zine
    - Cooking as a way of life, zine (Box 1)